hello and welcome everyone it is
September 14th 2023 and we are in the
course physics as information processing
it's lecture five
looking forward to this lecture and then
a little conversation Chris off to you
thank you
okay uh thank you Daniel uh and welcome
to session five of physics of
information processing
uh and today we're going to talk about
space time
and
um particularly about the idea that
space-time is emergent from information
processing
and this has now become a a very
mainstream idea in the quantum
information and quantum gravity
communities
and they're still of course
um
some people holding out for the idea
that space-time is fundamental
but I would say that at least in these
communities
uh
I expect it's become now the dominant
idea that space-time is not fundamental
that uh space-time is not part of
the basic ontology of reality or
something like that
and that instead space-time is a
construct
so that's what today's session is going
to be about
so for those of you who are just joining
or who would like a little review
uh we started this course talking about
Quantum information Theory
and the idea that Quantum information
theory is actually a new science about
systems that communicate across a
boundary
and the systems are all always called
Alice and Bob
for kind of historical reasons
and emphasize that this uh
new Sciences topological it's about
connectivity between systems it's not
geometric
so it doesn't assume a space-time
embedding
so it leaves open the possibility
that space-time is actually a construct
it doesn't assume space time up front
and uh
in the second session of the course I
think we
talked about how this boundary could
always be represented as an array of
qubits
and that what the systems
on each side of the boundary do to
communicate is prepare and then measure
the states of these qubits so they
communicate by exchanging
um
classical information
via a Quantum Channel
and this introduces a particular kind of
quantum noise whenever they don't share
of the reference frames that they use to
to prepare
the bits and measure the bits
so it's it's not
necessarily a perfect Communication
channel from a classical Fidelity point
of view but all of the noise is is
quantum noise it's not classical
and it always derives from differences
in the reference frames that are used by
the two agents
we reformulated the free energy
principle uh in this setting and uh the
free energy principle turns out to be
very simple
it turns out to be a classical limit of
the principle of unitarity which is just
the principle that information is
conserved
and we saw that the approach to
uh perfect alignment between the two
agents
or or perfect prediction on the part of
the two agents
becomes more challenging not
surprisingly a system complexity
increases
so the more complex
the communication the harder it is to
predict as one would expect
uh in the last session we talked about
how uh constraints on thermodynamic free
energy
induce compartmentalization in agents
so whenever
agents
interact with their environments in a
fairly complex ways
then they end up being compartmentalized
into compartments that have to
communicate classically
and this is solely a result of quantum
information Theory you don't have to
assume any biology
to get this compartmentalization
but clearly this is something that we
see in biological systems not only do we
see compartments we also also see
hierarchical control
uh which is likewise and a sort of
automatic outcome
of of
the theory for complex systems
and finally last time we talked a little
bit about
how these compartments communicate
and introduce the idea of communication
protocols that involve local operations
on a shared Quantum resource of some
kind
and classical communication and we
talked to Fairmount about how classical
communication
is a little bit problematic to
um
Define in quantum theory because of
course you're introducing classicality
and so you have to make some very
specific assumptions
about what's classical
and we'll see later on today
uh what the key assumption to gives you
classicality is
uh as we talk about space-time
but before uh I go into the topic of
space-time
I want to spend a little time
um okay so this sorry this is this is
where we're going we're talking about
space time and we'll talk about
applications to biology next time
but before we get going on this I want
to spend a little bit of time talking
about explanation
and this is motivated
by a question that came up a very long
question that touched on many different
topics that came up in the interactive q
a last time
and
a fair amount of that question had to do
with directly or indirectly
but the question of what scale-free
explanation looks like
and how it compares to
um scientific explanation in general
most of which is reductive
so I want to make a short detour
into the question of how
reductionist theories which all of you
are probably very familiar with relate
to scale-free theories
uh and and particularly the the free
energy principle is a scale-free theory
so it's it's a theory that's unlike uh
most of the theories that uh
most of you probably learned about in
college
so we're all familiar with reductionist
uh
theories and the reductionist idea of
scientific explanation which is is
really an outcome of philosophy of
science in the
20s and 30s people like Rudolph carnap
were among the first to actually
make precise what this idea of reductive
explanation is
but the basic idea is that uh the laws
or the Dynamics or the formalism
that describes Behavior at some micro
scale the behavior of little things
um
actually explains the behavior of big
things
so the basic reduction of this idea
is that uh what the little things are
doing
is what's important
and what big things are doing
uh are either emergent phenomena or
they're just Epi phenomenal they're
they're essentially just appearances
and this defines a fundamental scale
so the real assumption in any
reductionist theory is that there's some
fundamental scale at which the real
dynamics takes place
and everything else is just an
appearance or it's some sort of emergent
phenomenon and
uh I try to be very careful when I use
the word emergence because it's one of
the most ambiguous words in the
philosophy of science and people use it
to mean all sorts of different things
um
but whenever you say emergent
uh it always sort of implies the idea
that it's emergent from something
and so the idea of emergence is
essentially a reductionist idea
uh because it it at least implicitly
assumes that there's some micro scale
from which the macro scale is emergent
and uh so
the discussions of emergent phenomena
are offered very consistent with
reductionism even if they claim not to
be
and
we're all taught
um
that science is reductionist
and there's certainly people who who
publicly claim that science is reduction
is uh you know Richard Dawkins is
certainly a shining example of this
but I suspect that that a lot of
scientists just kind of play lip service
to reductionism Without Really believing
in it uh because they don't really
believe that the macroscopic phenomena
that they are studying life for example
is is completely determined by what's
going on at the microscale or or what's
going on at the micro scale plus some
some stochastic noise or something like
that
so I want to explicitly contrast this
with a scale-free theory
in a scale-free theory
is not simply a holistic Theory it's
much more precise in a scale-free theory
little things and big things obey the
same laws or they have the same Dynamics
or they're described by the same
formalism
so it's not that the macro scale is
emergent from the micro scale
the macro scale in the micro scale
actually obey the same laws
and the relationship between macro and
micro
is probably best stated as one of
implementation
uh
macro scale things have micro scale
components
and those micro scale components are
doing something or other
and whatever they're doing
implements the macro scale system and
Its Behavior
uh but this implementation
of
is not is not an explanation or at least
it's not an explanation all by itself
and the bumper sticker version of scale
free theories is just as above so below
whatever laws you have at the macro
scale are the ones the same ones you
have the micro scale and vice versa
so scale free theories and a sensors
simple it's the same Theory at every
level of description
so what is this idea of scale
and how does it relate to what we've
talked about in this course
well what we've talked about in this
course all has to do with what an agent
can observe on its boundary
so scale has to do with how information
is encoded on the boundary
and we can describe that scale in many
different ways
uh here's a commonplace way to describe
it in physics
uh by a relationship between energy and
distance or size
and
um
you've probably all heard of the Planck
scale
uh the Planck scale is the smallest
scale at which current physics makes any
sense
of
and
in energetic terms it's defined by
energies on the order of 10 to the 19th
gev which is giga electron volts
uh
the LHC the Large Hadron Collider in
Switzerland
um
it gets to about 10 to the fourth gev so
many many orders of magnitude less than
the Planck scale
so the point scale is extremely
energetic compared to what we can probe
experimentally
the Planck scale energy of 10 to the
ninth gev corresponds to a distance of
about 10 to the minus 35 meters which
is incredibly tiny
uh an intermediate scale on this diagram
is about the scale of a nucleon so for
example a proton or a neutron
they have a rest mass of about one gev
and a size of about one fintometer
so this intermediate scale is roughly
the scale of nuclear physics
and then if you if you go to our scale
the scale of things that are you know
about a meter in size of human beings
tables and chairs
lots of animals
the things we're most familiar with that
corresponds to an incredibly tiny energy
10 to the minus 5 electron volts is
about the energy of a photon of radio
radiation
and a meter is about the wavelength of
of
long Wave radio
so if you think about visible light
uh
has a wavelength of about 10 to the
minus 5 meters an energy of about an
electron volt so it's not surprising
though that visible light feels
energetic to us because it's it's orders
of magnitude above our natural scale of
energy
of this sort of thermal environment in
which we exist
so
it's the encoding scale and the boundary
that uh is going to relate
theories of things that we see
to each other
and this ends up giving a kind of
complicated picture if you think of
Alice interacting with Bob and measuring
things on the boundary
of
sorry I'm a little bit ahead of myself I
I just wanted to show you a picture of a
reductive Theory this is the Big Bang
You're all familiar with this
something happens at the Planck scale
and the entire universe results from it
by just a scale change
so this is this is a reductive Theory a
scale free theory is much more
complicated
so here's what a scale free Theory looks
like
uh Alice interacts with Bob
and she's looking at her boundary
and her boundary States the boundary
State she sees could be encoded at
different scales
so there may be a small scale scale one
and a bigger scale scale two
and what Alice is looking for is some
sort of theory
that relates the first scale the the
micro scale to the macro scale
and
so it's not that the micro scale came
first like it did in the Big Bang and
the macro scale came later
uh these are these are encodings that
can be happening simultaneously
and the theoretical task is to find
theories that relate between these
scales and these are implementation
theories or you might call them
embedding theories
from one scale into another
and what we want as a consistency
Criterion
is for these theories to be constant in
time so as Bob evolves in time
and so at Alice's are these encodings on
her boundary
she wants the relationship between
encoding the different scales to stay
constant because if it doesn't she'll
never be able to figure anything out
she'll just have this chaotic
relationship between things happening at
different scales and nothing will make
sense
so you have this complicated picture
in scale-free theories
and if you look at this and it seems
Vaguely Familiar or even vaguely even
very familiar
I'll then uh it should
because this is exactly the kind of
explanatory structure or semantic
structure that you have in computer
science
uh if you're studying the behavior of a
computer which is just some some piece
of Hardware some physical system
then you can describe what the that
piece of Hardware is doing at different
scales
and in fact what we call the hardware
level of description when we talk about
you know our laptops for example
is typically the level of description of
of
circuits of transistors inside
microprocessors we think of that as the
hardware level but of course that's just
a description too that's layered on top
of lots of much smaller scale Dynamics
all the way down to
the scale of of
atoms and eventually nuclei and
Elementary particles and all that other
stuff
so there's some Quantum stuff that's
going on that we describe as having a
classical Hardware level of bid Exchange
and then we describe the behavior
programs on top of that
so what we want what makes a computer
useful
is that we can assign
semantics to programs
and we can talk about semantic
relationships between programs for
example the relationship between
the internet
uh protocol stuff that Zoom is doing
and what you actually see on your user
interface and here on your user
interface
that needs to stay fixed over time
or Zoom becomes incomprehensible and and
not programmable and in fact not even
well defined as a as an algorithmic
system
and the same is true for the
relationship between the operating
system and the hardware description or
between the operating system and and
zoom as a program
so computer science Works in exactly
this scale-free way and so in a sense
of scale free explanation is very
familiar it's exactly the kind of
explanation that we have in computer
science
and that's why I refer to the
relationship between scales is one of
implementation
um because that's a term that we're
familiar with from thinking about
computers implementing programs
so what are these theories I mean if we
think in biological terms
uh we can think of Pathways being
embedded in a cell
uh where cells being embedded in tissues
all the way up to
um
niches of various kinds which may be
social niches being embedded in
ecosystems and ecosystems being embedded
in the biosphere
and so we have all of these essentially
semantic theories that talk about how
one scale embeds
in another scale
and if we have these sorts of of scale
transitions we can think of representing
the relationship between
transitions at different scales
in terms of the activity of some kind of
renormalization group
which is
transforming
entities and processes at one scale into
entities and processes at another scale
and I think in biology
we can at least put forward the
hypothesis
that
in all the way from
Pathways embedding in cells to
ecosystems embedding in the biosphere we
can put forward the hypothesis at least
that the renormalization group flow
across all of these scales is trivial
that is that the embedding theories all
have the same formal structure
that of
this the structure
that describes how Pathways embed into
cells is the same structure
that describes how ecosystems embed into
the biosphere
now I certainly can't prove that
uh I believe that it's likely
so I think it's an interesting
hypothesis to investigate
and this is uh n hypothesis that I want
to leave you with
as a result of this class is something
to think about
oh
to what extent and thinking about
biological systems or even social
systems
of
are the embedding theories the same
so
um
in thinking this way
that
the physics of the situation
is has the same formal structure as
computer science has in terms of
explanation
oh we're of course faced with a problem
which is that we're not just
reconstructing physics
we're talking about the physics of of
interacting observers we're talking
about the physics of communication
so we're modeling How We Do physics
and that makes our Theory
self-referential
and so we have to
face the music from girdle's theorem
which tells us essentially that powerful
self-referential theories can't be both
consistent and complete
and by powerful it I just mean powerful
enough to express arithmetic so not
terribly powerful
so
this becomes an issue that we have to
live with
uh
we we will always be faced with this uh
issue
of having to construct
meta theories
which tell us how our lower level
theories work
but we never get to the end of that
process we we never can get to theories
that are both consistent and complete
because our Tower of theories becomes
progressively actually more powerful
as it goes up
so so girdle
uh
in a sense poses a problem but in
another sense just tells us what life is
like as a scientist
oh that you can't have everything
all the time
doing science but we probably all
already knew that
so let's now talk about space uh end of
digression
and see how these ideas
apply
to a system or a tower of systems
that can construct a spatial embedding
in its World in its observed world
so let's start out thinking about a
system
that can see its environment
but what it sees as a completely uniform
environment where nothing is happening
so if you have a uniform environment
where nothing is happening
uh you can't distinguish one part of the
environment for another from another so
so there's no you have no sense of space
so what I want to do is
build up from scratch
what's needed to have a sense of space
and then we'll we'll talk a little bit
about what uh organisms are doing and I
think a very interesting question is if
you look at phylogeny
at what points in phylogeny what
lineages in phylogeny
actually need to have a sense of space
and what do they have to
have in terms of computational power
to have that sense of space
so if you just have a uniform
environment uh you don't have a sense of
space
but the first the first thing we can do
with an environment is is to divide it
up
into some number of parts that are
somehow distinguishable
so suppose we can segment the
environment into two different parts
and if you think about E coli for
example
uh E coli has a bunch of sensors on the
front and a bunch of effectors on the
back
so it can sense much more about the
front part of the environment than the
back part of the environment
so already with E coli you have this
kind of segmentation of the environment
into parts
but so far nothing is happening in this
environment we just have segments that
can be distinguished
so
let's consider an environment like this
that has distinguishable segments
uh what
one next wants to know about these
segments is whether they're next to each
other
and if we just have a bunch of segments
we just have a set
and a set doesn't have any order
or any relationship information
so I've I've drawn this environment as a
rectangle of rectangles but that's just
a representation
oh
and it looks like there are
relationships between these rectangles
but if they're if they're just a set
then there are no relationships
if we want to add relationships then we
have to add them explicitly
so let's add some connections
between these different segments of the
environment
how to turn that set into a graph
that says explicitly for example that
the light green segment is attached to
the light blue segment and it's also
attached to the dark green segment
and the dark blue segment is attached to
the light blue segment and attached to
the dark green segment
so now we have something that's that's
much more mathematically complicated
than a set we have a graph that has some
connection information so we have a
connection topology
now adding this topology does something
very important it breaks the exchange
symmetry
that is there if you just have a set so
if we just have a set
it doesn't make any difference if I
exchange for example the positions of
the upper right like blue segment with
the upper left like green segment
but if we have this connection topology
then it does make a difference
right I've I've
uh Twisted the graph around
and if I have to break connections to
exchange things then I've actually
changed the topology
so
adding a topology adding connections
can disrupt a symmetry that's there uh
if there if there is no topology
so now let's let's think about now we
have the structure that's required
to think about something happening
so suppose that
at some time is measured in the bit
counter time reference frame of the
observing system
happens so a DOT appears in the light
green segment
and uh we can express this actually in
the notation of quantum field Theory we
can think of
[Music]
um
the light green segment as a field
and the dot appearing is the occurrence
of an excitation in that field
and so we can write this notation that
says that the Green Field
was excited to produce a DOT
which is up Arrow Green Dot
and
sometime after that
oh it may turn out that the the dot
disappears in the Green Field
and some sort of dot appears down in the
dark blue field
and again we can write this in this kind
of creation and destruction operator
notation that that one has in Quantum
field Theory
and so this says that a
Green Field is no longer excited but now
the dark blue field is excited
so this doesn't
imply anything about these excitations
being the same in fact they're
completely different
uh one is an excitation of the Green
Field and one is an excitation of the
blue field
but at least now something is happening
in the environment
so
we can think about what does it take
for an observer to notice that something
is happening is in its environment it
has to be able to
to
detect
a change occurring in some segment of
its environment
and that change can involve
something happening or something
stopping happening in that segment of
its environment
but it doesn't uh yet have to have any
idea of what an object is
but we can add that
uh if the system has a memory
um
we can have the system connect
these events happening in different
parts of its environment
so if the system has a memory that has
some number of steps I'll say
in steps but here it could even just be
two steps
I'll
it can see transitions between these two
different states
where there's a dot in the Green Field
and then a dot in the in the dark blue
field and then a dot in the Green Field
and then a dot in the dark blue field
and then a dot in the Green Field Etc
so I've expressed this in this sort of
field Theory notation
um
over on the right side
and what this is is a flip-flop it's an
observed periodic Behavior
so this is the basic idea behind a clock
so any Observer that can see this
some number of of time steps internally
can interpret what's going on in its
external environment as a clock ticking
uh you can see some periodism
so
as long as you can have memory and the
ability to detect change
you can see periodic behavior in the
environment so you can see the
environment acting like a clock
so let's think a bit about what this
does and does not require
so seeing a clock in the environment
requires having distinguishable
non-exchangeable sectors of the
environment so you have to have this
connection topology that breaks the
exchange symmetry
it requires having these sectors
Implement some sort of flip-flop so
something periodic happening
and you have to have enough memory to
see that periodicity
but it doesn't require any sense of
object identity
so the excitation in the green part and
the excitation in the blue part can
still just be field excitations of the
green part of the blue part
oh it doesn't
there's there's nothing that says that
those have to be the same thing they
just have to appear and disappear in
some periodic way
and having a clock doesn't require a
metric space you don't need to have any
sense of distance defined on the
environment uh you just have to have
this segmentation
that is not rearrangeable
so this tells us something extremely
important which is that
time is more fundamental than space
I'm in the exterior environment is much
simpler and easier to observe than space
in the exterior environment
so for thinking biologically about
phylogeny
we might expect to see
organisms
that can detect periodic behavior in the
external environment long before they
can detect spatial organization in the
exterior environment
and we know that organisms uh even down
to to microbial mats can respond to the
diurnal cycle
so
we know that organisms in a sense can
detect environmental clocks
uh even organisms that we have no reason
to believe
divide the environment up into spaces or
the sort of space that we're used to
like a euclidean space
so now about adding space to this idea
of time in the environment
so
the next step is to be able to see
motion
and being able to see one thing
move from one segment of the environment
to another segment
as opposed to something happening in one
segment and then something happens in
another segment
what has to have this idea of object
persistence
that there's a thing that has an
identity
and its identity doesn't change over
time
and it doesn't change when you move it
someplace else and it appears someplace
else in the environment it's the same
object
so
this is an idea that psychologists call
object persistence
and it's an idea that physicists call
translational invariants
translational invariance
means two things it means that if I if I
have an object and I move it to a
different location I don't change the
object it's the same object that I move
from here to there
so the location doesn't change the
object
but it also means the reverse of that
it means that the object doesn't change
the location
uh by by container remains invariant
even though I move the object around in
it so these are kind of the two faces of
translational invariance and then the
two phases of object persistence
um
as the object moves through time its
identity remains fixed
and it doesn't change the time that it's
moving through
so if I'm measuring the moat it's motion
with a clock
uh moving the object doesn't change the
clock
these are clearly very classical ideas
uh and we talked about
earlier classical communication
and
when we talked about classical
Communication in for example the context
of of a bell epr experiment we talked
about The Observers being able to write
down some data
on a piece of paper or on a a disk drive
or something and hand those data to
someone else
so this is translational invariance the
data can't change when Alice gives it to
Bob
otherwise there isn't classical
communication taking place
and of course there's an up to noise
built into here
right the piece of paper might get wet
and the ink might run a little bit
but it's still the same message there's
still some identity being assumed
so
object persistence is not an idea we get
from quantum theory it's an idea that we
impose on top of quantum theory
and it's this idea that's intrinsically
classical
so we're looking right here at the
quantum to classical transition this is
it
this is what gets added to Quantum
Theory to get classical physics it's
this idea of object persistence
now once we have object persistence we
can kind of go to town constructing
space
um
and
here's how we do it
uh
we all we all learned about object
persistence this way uh when we were six
months old
doing motor babbling
and observing our hands and feeling how
our bodies worked
and seeing objects that we could could
manipulate and that didn't change when
we manipulated them
so this is the birth of object
persistence this is the birth of
classicality
uh in in human psychology
so now let's start thinking about
building a coordinate system what's a
coordinate system a coordinate system is
just a set of labels that are attached
to these segments of the environment
and to build a coordinate system you
have to have an origin
and An Origin means an object
something that's fixed
something that doesn't move around
and so a coordinate system requires the
ability to identify a stigmergic memory
requires the ident ability to find
something in the environment
that has a meaning
that stays constant over time
and that's that's what a stigmergic
memory is it's something in the
environment that provides us with a
memory resource that we can count on
being the same
and
it's having this fixed point
that allows us to label
these connected segments of the
environment
how the contain that contain objects
that move
and be able to say okay the object moved
from this part of the environment to
another part
and I can I can give those parts labels
with respect to this other part that
doesn't move
this origin point
and once I have this I can construct
other invariances
so for example I can consider an object
that rotates around this origin without
changing its identity
and that defines what's called
rotational invariance
and I can also talk about an object that
gets bigger and smaller
compared to this fixed point
and that defines radial distance
and if you think about the the baby in
the previous slide
that's doing motor babbling it sees
things getting smaller as it moves them
farther away
so the visual system does this
computation for us
and constructs this radial coordinate
for us with respect to our bodies or
specifically our heads our eyes
so uh in
in doing this this very early
motor activity we're actually building
the spatial coordinate system
uh for our brains that's implemented by
the hippocampus the place sells in the
hippocampus
and if I have an origin point in the
environment
uh I can also infer that I am moving
that I have changed my location with
respect to that object
and that's a considerably more
complicated inference because you have
to have a representation of the self of
you
to say I moved so this is something that
comes after you've developed this
spatial coordinate system you have to be
able to locate in a sense
metacognitively
a particular object that's you in that
coordinate system
so we're going to set that aside and now
talk about
adding some numbers so adding a metric
and adding a metric
requires another particular kind of
object
which is a ruler
uh a particular
fixed object that can be moved around
and it has translational invariance and
rotational invariance up to some
transformation up to some tensor
and in euclidean space that tensor is
the identity
so in a euclidean space you have
perfect translational and rotational
invariance
as you get into general relativity
then the ruler can actually change its
length as you rotate or the ruler can
change its length as it moves through
space
so effectively your space time can
deform the coordinates of your space
time could deform and that gives you the
representation of mass of course in
general relativity
so we talked uh several sessions ago
about
Quantum reference frames
and I used the example of rulers and
clocks as Quantum reference frames
so now we see how to construct those
uh from observations
and symmetry breaking and object
identity
all of which we need to define a Quantum
reference frame out in the environment
like a ruler
add notice that we don't need any of
that environmental stuff
to define those qrfs within our own
processing and in fact
uh the ones that exist within us
we have no direct access to
we can look at someone else's brain and
talk about their spatial representation
system but we can't look inside our own
brains and talk about our spatial
representation system
so this is how we get a metric space uh
from the ground up
and we've talked about this from a very
psychological or biological point of
view
starting from from sort of motor
capabilities uh
motor babbling for example
uh a measure of effort which gives you
some sense of mass
so if it's easy to move something it's
light and if it's hard to move something
it's heavy
and we understand that when we're six
months old because we can measure how
much force we're having to apply with
our muscles we have this we have a a
reference internally for this force that
we're applying
and we
use that internal measurement to
attribute this idea of Mass to things in
the environment
we have to have memory for manipulations
we have to be able to identify at
variances that Define objects
object persistence and we have to be
able to build a ruler
that we can move around and use to
define a metric space
it's very different from the way
physicists approach this
uh if you look at the physics literature
then people start with information
transfer they talk about uh entanglement
as a basic resource
um
there's a lot of discussion of bulk
boundary Duality and the most well-known
one is uh The Duality between Andy to
sitter space which is the sort of space
you see inside a black hole
and a conformal field Theory a Quantum
field theory on the boundary of the
black hole so
things you can see for example going on
on the horizon of a black hole or dual
to
the geometry and the interior
by this mathematical relationship
you can use that mathematical
relationship to construct a Quantum
error correcting code
oh
by using the symmetries of the field
Theory as a resource for redundancy that
allows you to represent the same thing
in different places
and as soon as you can do that you can
build up a network of elements that look
basically like elements of a lattice
and a lattice uh is a graph to which you
can assign
symmetric relationships and and you get
a metric space
and in physics typically the goal is to
get Einstein's equations out of this to
start with some information theoretic
sorts of constructs and get the
equations of general relativity
but what are the equations of general
relativity
I mean these are things that Einstein
derived by doing fairly simple thought
experiments
um
using the invariances
of
ordinary euclidean space
combined with ideas from special
relativity about the speed of light
being constant
and he added the the principle of
equivalence which is the idea that
uh
essentially mass and acceleration are
the same thing
uh or the gravity and acceleration are
the same the weight and acceleration of
the same time
so it's at least reasonable to expect
that
uh
this inferential process
that's going on in theoretical physics
is generating the same thing although in
a very formalized way
that we can generate by thinking about
how organisms deal with their
environments
and so I want to
leave this with you as the second
hypothesis here
one the first one was the hypothesis
about
a trivial renormalization group flow
across scales and biology
the second hypothesis is that these two
approaches to emergent space-time are
actually giving us the same information
and maybe starting out with the same
information in fact
that we may be able to think about
these fundamental building blocks
of information flow and entanglement
in terms of the sorts of perceptual
relationships that we've been talking
about
in this class
so there's our second hypothesis
to think about going forward
and I just want to leave you with the
idea that organisms at least
manage this very interesting
process
um
that we can think of starting as
starting with with this the construct of
memory
organisms have memory multiple scales
and it's memory that allows them
to formulate the idea that there are
objects
and as soon as you have objects that
persist
you have a source of redundancy
so you can do error correction
and if you can do error correction if
you can move the same thing from one
place to another
and have it encode the same information
then you can build space talk
and as soon as you have space time you
can use the space time as more memory
you can use the space time itself as an
error correcting code
oh because space time has the nice
ability to hold lots of copies
of some informative structures so you
can build libraries or you can build
computers or you can build the internet
if you have SpaceTime
which gives you more memory which gives
you more object persistence which gives
you more error correction
and the circle just spins around
so organisms do this
and the question is how does it get off
the ground
and
uh next time we can at least speculate
about that kind of
origin of Life type of question in the
context of the fep
and it's it's realization in simple
systems of communicating Observers
so uh as always I encourage you to use
the interactive q a
uh the fifth discussion session with
Andrew who's unfortunately not here
today
will be the last day of September uh
Saturday at five as usual uh five
o'clock European Time eight o'clock
California time
and then the last session of the class
will be the 12th of October
so uh thank you very much and I look
forward to your questions in the
interactive q a
often
thank you Chris um can I ask some short
questions
sure all right
so first from Lana wrote is the
periodicity the time lengths between and
during the excitations built in
so this was when we had the four cells
and there was the inklings of a clock
coming into play
I think the simplest answer is that
um
if nothing else is happening
in the environment except this periodic
Behavior
then uh
the
it's not actually meaningful to talk yet
about the time between the events
so if if I have a if I have
a periodic a system that's that's
quasi-periodic for example
uh
and nothing else is going on in my
environment
then I can't distinguish that from a
perfectly periodic system
because I would have to have a perfectly
periodic reference
to know that the other system was
aperiodic
and if you think about the internal
clock
being driven by information flow into
the system
then something has to be happening in
the environment for information to be
flowing into the system and being
counted
so uh again as we talked about a few
sessions ago
the internal memory only gets updated
when something happens
so internal and external get tied
together
and I and this is this is why we can use
external clocks
but it's also why we depend on external
clocks
uh because our
our intuitive sense of time is very
malleable
and so we we actually as humans use
external clocks
to correct for the malleability of our
own uh intuitive sense of time
wow and there's probably a lot to be
said for that procrustean nature of
having the chronometer the clock on the
wall and the tick tick tick
as an evolutionarily novel ruler of time
playing a logistical role in
time-bound Society
yeah and you know think of think of
earlier clocks that earlier cultures
have used and that animals use I mean we
have the the solar clock the lunar clock
Etc
and you know the the orbit of venous
clock that was so important to the
Mayans and so on
so we we there are lots of available
clocks in the environment
uh if you have the ability to notice
them and and enough memory to realize
that they're clocks
awesome all right here's a question from
upcycle Club they wrote
how does representing the network
structure and Dynamics with Quantum
embeddings affect the semantic
interpretation of the network
oh
the the embedding theory is the simplest
semantic interpretation of the network
so
um
and again a good way to think of this
is through the lens of computer science
you know as soon as you have a
programming language that allows uh
variable binding
then you've built a very simple kind of
semantics into the language
um if you have some if you have X as a
variable
and you have variable binding then at
different
times in the execution of the program
uh X can have different causal
consequences for Downstream computation
because it's been bound to a different
value so it has different semantics
so the semantics of x
again go back to go back to Gregory
Bateson
uh the the basis of semantics is
differences that make a difference make
a difference to behavior make a
difference to actionability
so uh variable binding gives you
differences that actually make a
difference to what the program does
of so
what is that
that
is the semantics that's assigned by your
embedding Theory
um between what the programming language
is doing and what the operating system
is doing and so forth
and I I think it's no surprise that
um
the semantics of programming languages
end up being
represented with these very general
mathematical constructs uh like category
Theory
which are essentially
uh tools for representing arbitrary
arbitrary relations
between systems
and that's what embedding theories are
there
uh theories that that state
relationships between systems
awesome and very
provocative to explore
on the biological and life and on the
space time and matter sides which are of
course
seamlessly integrated
through if only our own experiences
yeah this this is another place where
it's useful to go back to this
difference between
reductive theories and and scale free
theories and scale free theories are all
about semantics
because they represent the existence of
stuff happening at different scales and
so they naturally raise the question of
of what's what are these relationships
uh what are these embedding theories
and
in reductive theories uh there's a very
deep sense in which semantics doesn't
matter
like there's if if you think that's that
all that's going on that's important is
the stuff that's going on at the Planck
scale
then
you don't need any semantics right and
so oh
you you see this in late 60s you know
early 70s
uh old-fashioned AI
where uh people talk about
uh
computation is purely syntactic and this
is a very reductionist view of
computation it leaves out the semantics
and without the semantics the
computation is useless it doesn't tell
us anything at all unless we can map it
to something
so
um
we have this
philosophy of science tradition that
tells us that semantics is not important
and we end up with tools like the fep
that essentially tell us that semantics
is all important
and from a biological point of view
you know the most natural response is of
course we knew that all the time that's
why we're doing biology
so that all of this all of this ties
together
would you say that fep says semantics is
important
and then what does it say about what
semantics are important or is that
entirely left up to the modeler
well it tells you a lot about what's
important of or the system itself
right the system itself is dealing with
its environment
and it's it's trying to increase its
predictive power
so it's building a theory of the
environment
and that theory is intrinsically
semantic right it's about the
environment
and it's actionable right the the theory
is meant to drive action on the
environment
that will either yield more information
or get the environment to to you know
behaved to do what I'm predicting it's
going to do
so
uh I I think the fep has intrinsically
semantic in that sense that it's about
an agent modeling its environment
yes and about the semantics of action as
opposed to a partial or Limited
semantics of passive inferors or
semantics of abstraction
which kind of leaves the the important
link between the agent and the
environment through sense making and
decision selection basically unaddressed
because it's kind of descar you know in
the thought experiment in the room and
here when we actually engage with the
boundary of the room
that's where we start
yeah yeah the fep
ly destroys this
this classical notion of of the passive
Observer
as as does quantum theory you there are
no passive observers in quantum theory
so this this is a construct that we
inherited from a classical world view
that is is seriously misleading
a lot more to say but that's a great
place to end thank you Chris
okay thank you Daniel and and thanks to
you all and and uh ask questions
see you next time cheers